<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The scorner incapable of true wisdom a sermon before the Queen at White-hall, October 28, 1694 / by Francis Atterbury ...</title>
            <author>Atterbury, Francis, 1662-1732.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B17322</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12566922</idno>
  <idno type="VID">200282</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240950207</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing A4152</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12566922</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B17322)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 200282)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 953:35)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The scorner incapable of true wisdom a sermon before the Queen at White-hall, October 28, 1694 / by Francis Atterbury ...</title>
                  <author>Atterbury, Francis, 1662-1732.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Bennet ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. 22</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Wisdom --  Sermons.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:200282:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:200282:1"/>
            <p>Mr. <hi>ATTERBURY</hi>'s SERMON BEFORE THE QUEEN.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:200282:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:200282:2"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Scorner Incapable of True Wisdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A SERMON BEFORE THE QUEEN AT WHITE-HALL, <hi>October</hi> 28. 1694.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Francis Atterbury,</hi> Student of <hi>Christ-Church,</hi> and Chaplain in Ordinary to Their Majesties.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Published by Her Majesties special Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Bennet,</hi> at the <hi>Half Moon,</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard. 1694.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:200282:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:200282:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON ON PROVERBS xiv. 6.</head>
            <q>A Scorner seeketh Wisdom, and findeth it not.</q>
            <p>IT is the Wisest among the Children of Men, who speaks; and about That in which We are most nearly concern'd, and He was most immediately conversant, even the Method of attaining True Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; It becomes us therefore to give the most fixt and serious Attention, we can, to what he is saying:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Scorner,</hi> says he, <hi>seeketh Wisdom, and findeth it not.</hi> Where, we are first to enquire, Who it is, that is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presented to us under the Character of <hi>a Scorner;</hi> and then in what Sense he is said to <hi>seek Wisdom,</hi> but <hi>not to find it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Scorner,</hi> is One, who is frequently mention'd in this Book of <hi>Proverbs;</hi> and whom the Author of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:200282:4"/>it has levell'd many of his wise sayings against. We find in the <hi>Psalms,</hi> and <hi>Prophetic</hi> Writings also, many Glances at him, many Complaints of him. So that the Nation of the <hi>Jews</hi> did, it seems, abound mightily with This sort of Men; and They were a Great and Particular Grievance to the Followers of True Piety and Wisedom.</p>
            <p>Their Character seems, in short, to have been this. They were Men, that, with much adoe, had made a shift to get rid of Good Principles, and such stiff Opinions as they found inconsistent with a Loose Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise. As they had not any Religion themselves, so Their Way was to despise Those who had; to look down with Pitty and Contempt upon a poor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded Under-World; Beasts of Burthen that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd, in a Track, after their Leader; Slaves to receiv'd Rules, and Precarious Opinions, to Foolish Empty Forms and Observanses; but who never once reason'd freely, or thought for Themselves. They were unfortunately fallen into a Time, wherein fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Commotions hapned in the <hi>Jewish</hi> State (as the Case was remarkably in the Age before <hi>Solomon</hi> came to the Throne) and had seen several Sorts of Men up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>permost, and, consequently, several Notions of Things prevailing by Turns, This contributed mightily to unsettle their Thoughts, or (as They call'd it doubtless) to <hi>inlarge</hi> 'em; to create in 'em a flight Opinion of the Eternal Differences of Right
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:200282:4"/>and Wrong, Good and Evil; and to make 'em laugh at Those, who were Eager on any Side, or for any Cause whatsoever, which They did not get by.</p>
            <p>They evidently saw that Some, who set up for Greater Purity, and a Demurer Shew and Face of Religion than their Neighbours, were really Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeits, and meant nothing, at the bottom, but Their Own Interest. And they wisely resolv'd, upon This, that All Religion was, like Theirs, a Convenient Trick and Pretence onely; invented by Cunning men to keep silly People in awe, to make Princes Reign safely, and the Priesthood Live Easily. But as for Them, They knew better things, than to fall in With the Herd, and to give themselves up to be ridden by the Tribe of <hi>Levi:</hi> The Poorest and most Contemptible Tribe of the Twelve, who had no Lott, no Inheritance amongst 'em; but liv'd upon the Cheat of Sacrifices and Offerings, and upon driving a Gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Traffick for the Good Things of This World, paid down to Them <hi>here,</hi> by promising and preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up to Those they dealt with, a Recompence in Another World <hi>hereafter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor were These men content to injoy this Secret, which They had Thus found out, quietly among themselves; but set up openly for Proselytes and a Party; for running down all Religion, and for laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Piety and Virtue out of Countenance: so that a Good and Honest Man was sure to be Their Mark
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:200282:5"/>wheresoever they found him, and They were ever <hi>shooting out Their Arrows against him, even Bitter Words.</hi> And This was come to that pass, that the True Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God did almost sink under the Affliction; and did make it matter of Publick Request to God in the Solemn Service of the Church, to be freed from it. <hi>Have mercy upon us, O Lord,</hi> said They, <hi>have mercy upon us, for we are exceedingly filled with Contempt. Our Soul is exceedingly filled with the Scorning of Those that are at Ease, and with the Contempt of the Proud.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is, in some Measure, the Character of That man, who, in the Language of the Text, is call'd <hi>A Scorner:</hi> And You see now in what Sense he is said to <hi>seek Wisdom,</hi> but <hi>not to find it.</hi> For the meaning of that is plainly this; that He pretends to know more, and to see further, than the rest of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; to have made freer Enquiries after Truth, and to have shaken off the Prejudices of Education more Throughly; He sets up for examining Things to the bottom, without taking 'em upon Trust, or relying on the Authority of any Man. What God is pretended to have said in the Holy Writings, What Wise and Good Men have said in all Ages and Countries of the World, he is not concern'd to know. To the <hi>Oracles of Right Reason he goes</hi> (by Right Reason always meaning his Own) and from thence he enquires what he is to think, and to do:
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:200282:5"/>raises some Fancyful Scheme of things to himself, frames some Particular Set of Opinions; and then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyces in the mighty Discovery he has made, and wonders at the Rest of the World, that they do not fall in with it, and adore it. Now these Pretences the Wise man tells us are vain, and these searches are vain: He has taken a great deal of pains, only to be out of the way, and to miss the mark which he aims at. <hi>A Scorner seeketh Wisdom, and findeth it not!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having, thus largely, open'd the Sense of the Text, I shall endeavour, in what follows, to justifie the Truth of the Observation contain'd there, by shewing You, how it comes to pass, that the Men who thus set up for a more than ordinary pitch of Wisdom and Sense, by Contemning Religion, and Deriding the Professors of it, do always, and must always fail of the End which they propose to themselves; since whatever Abilities they may have in Other matters, yet they are the most unqualified and incapable of all men, to make impartial Enquiries after Divine Truth, and to discern between That and Error.</p>
            <p>There are <hi>Four</hi> Things that particularly unfit a Man for such a Task, a very <hi>Proud,</hi> or a very <hi>Suspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious</hi> Temper, <hi>False Wit,</hi> or <hi>Sensuality.</hi> And These are the Chief and Prevailing Ingredients in the Composi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of That man, whom we call a Scorner. The Two Last do generally, and in most instances, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to him; but the Two First are Essential to him▪ and inseparable from him.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:200282:6"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Pride</hi> is that Ruling Quality which (of all others) has the most considerable share in him; <hi>Proud and Haughty</hi> Scorner is his <hi>Name,</hi> says <hi>Solomon,</hi> elsewhere. And agen, <hi>There is a Generation, O how lofty are their Eyes! and Their Eylids lifted up !</hi> The truth is, there never was, nor ever can be a settled Contempt of Religious Principles, that is not built upon <hi>Pride, i. e.</hi> upon an undue Value which a Man has for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, and for his own Opinion, and a Disregard for every thing besides. And therefore the Author of that Fantastical Book, the <hi>Leviathan,</hi> does at the very Entrance of it, very honestly, and in Terms, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess that he is a Man, who <hi>Loves his own Opinions.</hi> And so doubtless does every Man too, who treads in his Steps, thô he does not own it so frankly, or perhaps know it so throughly. Indeed a Modest Humble man can hardly bring himself once to think of shaking off common receiv'd Principles, and going against the United Wisdom of mankind: or, if he should think of it, yet will he never venture to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish that Thought, but will conceal it as carefully, as he would his own Bosom Infirmity, or the Secret of his Friend. 'Tis the Presumptuous and Proud man only, that dares to trample on those Truths, which the rest of the World reverence, and can sit down quietly in the assurance that He alone is in the Right, and all mankind beside in the Wrong.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:200282:6"/>
            <p>Now, I say, as there is no One Quality, that sticks more closely to a Scorner, than That of Pride, so is there none that is a greater Enemy to just Think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and to an impartial Search after Truths of all kinds; especially after those, which relate to Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Piety. And no wonder therefore, if, on This Account, the Scorner, thô he <hi>seek Wisdom, yet findeth it not. Pride</hi> makes a man seem sufficient in his own Eyes for all manner of Speculations and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiries, and therefore puts him indifferently upon the pursuit of all Knowledge, and the determination of all Doubts, without giving him Leave to distrust himself in the least, or once to consider, which way his Genius and Abilities lie. Hence it comes, that the Man, not being duly Qualified for Every Search, or, if he were, yet not having leisure and opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity enough to go through with it, is fain to take up with slight and superficial accounts of things; and then, what he wants in true Knowledge, to make up in down right Assurance. As soon as he has touch'd on any Study, he immediately seems to himself to have master'd it; is as Positive in his Opinions, and as hardy in his Assertions, as if the Thoughts of his whole Life had been directed That way only: Which is, as if a Coaster, who has gone from Port to Port only, should pretend to give a better description of the Inland Parts of a Country, than Those who have travelled it all over. But this, I say, is the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:200282:7"/>mischievous Nature of Pride; it makes a Man Grasp at every thing; and, by Consequence, comprehend nothing effectually and throughly; and yet (which is worst of all) incline, him to despise and contradict those that do. It gives him just enough understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to raise an Objection, or a Doubt, but not enough to lay it; which, as it is the meanest and most despicable, so it is also the most dangerous State of mind, a man can be in; and by so much the more dangerous, as the Subject he is upon is more important, and the Errors more fatal which he runs into in managing it. He that is but Half a Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher is in danger of being an Atheist; an Half Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sician is apt to turn Empiric; an Half Bred man is conceited in his Address, and troublesome in his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versation. Thus it is in all matters of Speculation or Practise; He that knows but a little of 'em, and is very confident of his own strength, is more out of the way of True Knowledge than if he knew nothing at all. Now there is, I say, a Natural Tendency in Pride, to put a man into this State, and therefore it must needs be a Quality very opposite to the Search and Attainment of True Wisdom.</p>
            <p>And then, supposing a Proud man to be once in the Wrong, it is almost impossible, that he should ever be set Right again; He is plac'd above the reach of that great means of amendment, Reproof; <hi>A Scorner heareth not rebuke,</hi> says <hi>Solomon:</hi> and therefore as his
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:200282:7"/>Pride led him into a mistake at first, so will it be sure to keep him there; and to harden him in his way, against whatever wise men can think, or say of him.</p>
            <p>Thus, I say, is Pride an Enemy to the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Truth in general, but most of all does it hinder men form discerning Sacred Truths, and the Doctrines of Reveal'd Religion. A Proud man is very hardly brought to digest the Humble Duties of the Cross, or to receive the Mysteries of Christia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity: the One are too low for him, and he cannot stoop to the Practise of 'em; the other are too high for his Understanding, and he cannot tell how to entertain any thing as true, that he does not perfectly comprehend. If he cannot give himself a certain plain account in what Manner, and to what End God did a thing, he wisely resolves, that therefore he did it not all. If he has not as clear an Idea of every Term in an Article of Faith, as he has of Those in a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematical Proposition, 'tis presently Unphilosophical absurd, and foolish; invented by Those whose Interest it is, to puzzle mens understandings, that they may have their Wills and Affections at Their Service.</p>
            <p>And This puts Us in mind also of that <hi>Second</hi> Great <hi>Ingredient</hi> in the Character of a Scorner which we propos'd to consider, a strange and <hi>unreasonable Suspicion,</hi> by which he doubts of every thing be hears, and distrusts every man he converses with; Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:200282:8"/>the World to be all Cheat and Imposture; that there is no Sincerity, no Honesty any where; but that every man is continually Studying how to put a Trick upon his Neighbour. Without This Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per it might be Easily prov'd, that a man cannot bring himself to run down Religion and the Profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors of it; and, with it, it is impossible, I think, to arrive at True Wisdom. Indeed to be Cautious and upon our Guard in receiving Doctrines, and not easily to give up our assent to every Tale that is told us, is a piece of great Prudence and very requisite in such a multiplicity of Opinions as there is in the world, to preserve us from Error: But then we may carry this point too farr; we may be so scrupulous and circumspect in admitting the Testimonies of men, as to reject some Good Witnesses among several Bad ones; and to deceive our Selves often times for very fear of being deceiv'd by Others. A General <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>distinguishing suspicion</hi> is as apt every whit to mislead a man, as a too Easie and Unwary Credulity. And This is remarkably the Case of the Scorner. He is so possess'd with the Notion of <hi>Priest-Craft,</hi> and <hi>Pious Frauds,</hi> as to apply it indifferently to all Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, and to Every thing in Religion. He is so afraid of having his Understanding impos'd on in Matters of Faith that he stands equally aloof from all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions of that kind, whether True or False. Which is, as if a Man should refuse to receive any
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:200282:8"/>Mony at all, because there is a great deal goes about that is False and Counterfeit; or resolve not to make a Friendship or Acquaintance with any man; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause many men are not to be trusted. Certainly this is a very great Instance of Folly, and in what Breast soever it is, cannot possibly be consistent with True Prudence and Wisdom. An extremity of Suspicion in an Inquirer after Truth, is like a Raging Jealousie in an Husband, or a Friend; It leads a man to turn all his thoughts toward the ill-natur'd side, and to put the worst construction upon every thing, and (in Consequence of that) for once that he is really in the Right, in his Guesses and Censures, to be very often and very much in the Wrong.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Third</hi> part of the Character of that Man we are discoursing of, is <hi>False Wit;</hi> or a Way of exposing Things Sacred and Serious by passing a Bold Jest upon 'em, and Ridiculing arguments instead of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futing 'em. The very name of <hi>a Scorner</hi> will tell us, that This is One of his most belov'd Accomplish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: And I am sure it is such an One, as can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver conduce to his Getting right Impressions of Things, and can hardly ever be made consistent with his Having 'em. Wit indeed, as it implies a certain un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>common Reach and Vivacity of Thought, is a very Useful Talent; very fit to be employ'd in the Search of Truth, and very capable of assisting us to discern and find it: but in the Way, in which the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:200282:9"/>Scorner exerts it, the Way of Satyr and Prophane Drollery, it betrays a man into a Thousand Errors, for One that it discovers to him. Men of Quick and Lively parts are apt to give themselves a loose be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Plain Reason and Common Sense; and to say many things not exactly Right and True in order to say something New and Surprizing. Their Great Aim is, in general, <hi>to please;</hi> and, in order to that, they must bend all their Wit that way, to which the Corrupt Nature of man is inclin'd, and be sure always to speak <hi>against</hi> that which is uppermost. This gives 'em a Light and Trifling, instead of a Serious and Manly Spirit; and makes 'em think, they have answer'd all the Wisest Reasons that can be brought for any thing, if they have but clap'd a <hi>Nickname</hi> upon it, and dress'd up a Grave and Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable Truth in so Odd a disguise, as to raise Mirth and Laughter from it. Thus a late Person, Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent for Wit and Wickedness, till a Death-bed made him more Serious, and gave him truer apprehensions of Things, us'd to please himself mightily with that Thought, that the doing of a Miracle was onely <hi>shewing of a Trick:</hi> and when he had once re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presented the Thing to himself under that Light Image, he could hardly be brought to think reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently of it ever afterwards; or to allow the strong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Arguments that could be brought for the Truth of Miracles, a due and impartial Consideration.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:200282:9"/>And thus also the great Leader of the Libertines of This Age (whom we have already had occassion to mention) thought he had said something very preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial to the <hi>Divinity</hi> of Christ, when he had Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slated, after an Absurd Manner, the Greek Word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>(which by S. <hi>John</hi> is apply'd to Him) and blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mously told us, that That was as much as to say, in Our Tongue, the <hi>Verb of God:</hi> And again, he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to give a mighty Blow to the Doctrine of <hi>Grace,</hi> by strictly enquiring into the meaning of those Two Expressions, generally us'd by Divines concerning it, To wit <hi>Infusion,</hi> and <hi>Inspiration;</hi> and by informing us, that they signified, in plain <hi>English, Inpowring</hi> and <hi>Inblowing.</hi> I bring These Instances, to shew, how far a Scorner may be led out of the Way of Truth, by a little Knack of playing upon Things and Words, which he miscals <hi>Wit;</hi> and upon which he shall value himself more, and be wiser in his own Conceipt than <hi>Seven Men that can render a Reason.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Fourth</hi> and Last Thing, from whence we propos'd to give an account of His Deceptions, was <hi>Sensuality:</hi> and that This too does, for the most part, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company a Contempt of Religion, I appeal to the Observation and Experience of every One that Hears me. Look round the World, and You shall seldom find a man Loose in his Principles, that is not so in his Manners too. There may possibly be, now and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:200282:10"/>then, in an Age, an Instance of some Cold Phleg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matic man, that shall set up for overturning Religion and Morality, merely for the sake of Contradiction, or to get himself a Name by it, without the design of Indulging his Own Appetites, in so doing: But This is a very Rare Case; generally the <hi>Scorners</hi> are, as S. <hi>Peter</hi> and S. <hi>James</hi> have Unanimously describ'd 'em, in their several Epistles; <hi>Men who walk after their Own Lusts.</hi> Accordingly, we may observe, that This Scorning Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor has been most prevalent in Those Ages of the World, in which the Love of Pleasure, and the Arts of Ease and Luxury did most abound; and is commonly Incident to Men, at that Time of their Lives, when their Lusts are most ungovern'd, and their Blood boils hottest. 'Tis chiefly the Young Robust Sinner that indulges himself in it, <hi>whilst</hi> he is in the midst of his Enjoyments: for thô a Man may continue on this Temper in the Latest Years of his Life, yet he generally takes it up much Earlier.</p>
            <p>Now the Sensual Man, is, of all men living, the most Improper for inquiries after Truth, and the least at Leisure for it. He is never Sedate and Cool, and therefore not able to fix his attention to a Point, and go through with it. He is never Disinterested and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial; and therefore not capable of deliberating Freely. He is already under the Dominion and Power of his Lust; and perhaps likes to be so, and is very unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to shake off his Chains. Now such a Man, so
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:200282:10"/>qualified, is, no doubt, a very incompetent Judge of Divine Truth, and very unfit to consider the Pleas that are brought for it. His Search into These things is like to be with no great Evenness and Fairness; How can it? When he comes with strong Wishes that he may find it all a mistake. Indeed, when a Man allows himself in all sorts of Impurities, and is determin'd to go on in 'em; and yet finds himself un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Troublesome Restraint of Principles, and the Dread of Religion, that hangs continually over him, the onely way for him to pursue his Enjoyments, and yet be easie, is to set his Face directly against the Doctrines of Religion, that give him any check or disturbance, and resolve to get rid of 'em as soon as he can. And he may put the Thoughts, which arise in him upon This occasion, together; and make a Book of 'em, if He pleases; and then tell us, that This is a sober Enquiry after Truth; and a free discussion of the Point in debate: but there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of that in it. He thinks of Truth just as a man does of his <hi>Enemy,</hi> with Spite and Anger, and a Design only of finding out whatever may blast and expose it. This is a strange contumelious way of treating Divine things, and would tempt a Good man to return the affronts done to Vertue and Piety, by opening the Characters of Those who do 'em; in which we should always find, that Sensuality and Loosness of Life had a very great and particular share.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:200282:11"/>But Some Men, who Write pretended <hi>Histories of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> are beholding to the Real Religion of Others, that Their Histories are not written.</p>
            <p>Thus have I run through those four several Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which remarkably belong to the Character of a Scorner; and shewn You, how Each of 'em contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes to misinform and mislead Him in his pursuit of Wisdom; so that, supposing him really and in good Earnest to <hi>seek</hi> it, yet thus setting out and thus Qualified, it is not at all probable that he should <hi>find</hi> it.</p>
            <p>And now the Plain and Obvious Use we are to make of This Discourse, is, to satisfie our selves from hence how it has come to pass, that the True Religion, all along, in the several Ages of the World, have not been entertain'd, by many of the seeming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Wittiest and Wisest amongst the Children of Men.</p>
            <p>To This startling Question, We can now give a Short and Easie Answer, from the Observation of the Text; <hi>They were Scorners.</hi> They were either Proud and Opinionative Men, that could not endure to learn the plain humble Lessons of Piety and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness; especially from Such as They had no Esteem of, no value for. Or their Minds were tainted with an ill natur'd, and unreasonable Supicion, which, from finding out Some Cheats in Religion, led 'em to pronounce All Religion a Cheat. They had a Talent perhaps at Ridiculing Honest Rules and Maxims, and making Sport with Things Sacred
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:200282:11"/>and Serious; and therefore to have own'd any fix'd Scheme of Religious Principles, would have been a mighty Damp to their Imaginations, and have taken away from 'em the Subject of above half their Wit and Pleasantness. Or, Lastly, They were Men of <hi>Sensual</hi> and <hi>Impure Lives,</hi> who were resolv'd to make their Opinions and their Pleasures as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistent as they could; and who therefore were oblig'd, in point of Interest, to disbelieve every thing that made against 'em.</p>
            <p>This is the Short and True Account of the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and will appear to be so, if we cast our Eyes backward on the Story of the World, and consider, Who they have been, that have rejected the True Religion all along from the Creation down to this Time.</p>
            <p>In the Old World, <hi>Noah,</hi> Who was the onely man that preserv'd the Worship of the True God in his Family, seems to have been an honest plain hearted man; <hi>just and perfect in his Generation,</hi> (as he is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed in Scripture) <hi>and walking with God.</hi> The Rest of the World are said to have Eaten and Drunken, to have Married and been given in Marriage, <hi>i.e.</hi> They were men who liv'd in all the Enjoyments of Sense, who revell'd, and took their fill of all the Good Things of this World; and, to be sure, were very Merry, and very Bitter upon Those who did not. How did they deride that Grave Preacher of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:200282:12"/>and his Precise Family, when He and his Sons talk'd to 'em of Righteousness, Temperance and Judgment! especially, when he told 'em that there was Such a Flood coming, and that he was building That Ark to preserve himself and his House<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, what a Jest was he to the Men of Parts and Pleasure! How many Scornful and Gay things were said upon this Occasion, while the Work went forward, by Those, who thought themselves very wise, and Him very Foolish! But the Fountains of the great Deep were broken up, and the Windows of Heaven open'd, and then they began to change their Opinions when (alas!) it was too late to learn.</p>
            <p>In the next great Period after the Flood, the true Religion was confin'd to the single Nation of the <hi>Jews:</hi> and one may think it strange at first sight that (if it were the True Religion) it should be so; that the wise and knowing part of mankind should not discern the strength of the Evidence that was brought for the Divinity of That way of Worship, nor receive the God of <hi>Israel</hi> for Their God; that <hi>All Nations did not fall down before him, all Kingdoms did not do him service.</hi> But, if We consider a little further, we shall be satisfied, that the true reason of Mens Incredulity throughout this long Period of time, was, a Mean and Contemtible Notion they had entertain'd, of the <hi>Jewish</hi> People, of their Rites
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:200282:12"/>and Ceremonies. The Wise Men of the East in the Earliest Ages, and the Philosophers of the West in Later Times, had too high an Opinion of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, and too low an one of that Little, Narrow-soul'd, Superstitious Nation, to submit themselves to be taught by 'em. The <hi>Jews</hi> were a Proverb and a By-word to the rest of the World, the perpetual Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of their Contempt and Reproach: And who would have thought (may we suppose one of those Wise Heathens to have said) that Truth should have lain hid among such an <hi>Odd</hi> sort of People in such a little Spot of the World.</p>
            <p>And Thus, Again, when Christianity first ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd, it made no great Progress among the Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puters of this World, among the Men of Wit and Sublety; for this very Reason, <hi>because</hi> they were Scorners. The Gospel was to the <hi>Jews,</hi> to the most Learned and Proud Sect among the <hi>Jews,</hi> (the <hi>Pharisees</hi>) a <hi>Stumbling-block,</hi> and to those of highest Repute among the <hi>Greeks, foolishness.</hi> The Great pretenders to knowledge Every Where unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mously contemn'd and derided it, as a poor and low Systeme of Principles, and could never once think of humbling their minds to entertain the sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity of the Gospel.</p>
            <p>And no wonder therefore, if, in some Ages after Christianity, We find not much said to the advantage of it, in the Writings of Those Eminent <hi>Greeks</hi> and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:200282:13"/>
               <hi>Romans,</hi> who are allow'd to have been the best Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters of Polite Thought and Expression. Alas! <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyry</hi> must have vail'd his great name for Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, and <hi>Lucian</hi> in great measure have forgone his Skill in Satyr; The Witty Libertines of those Times must have parted with much of the Esteem they had, and with most of their Pleasures, if they had once admitted the Truth of Christianity: and therefore they agreed in running down the Reputation of That, that they might not lose their Own.</p>
            <p>And as it was immediately after our Saviours coming, so has it been ever since to this very day. The Doctrines of the Cross have never in any Age met, nor will they ever in any future Age meet with a kind and hearty reception, among Those, who <hi>sit in the Seat of the Scorners.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But let it not therefore deject us, That there are Many whom the World Esteems, who yet esteem not Us, and Our Holy and Undefiled Religion! and let us not suspect our selves upon that Account, as being out of the way and imposed upon, because Men of greater Reach, and perhaps a more improv'd Understanding than We, are not of Our Mind. <hi>Solomon,</hi> who was certainly a Man of Understanding, and who was of our Mind, does, in a very few Words (which I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not repeat too often) afford us a thorough Solution of the Case, <hi>A Scorner</hi> (saith he) <hi>seeketh Wisdom and findeth it not.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:200282:13"/>
            <p>From the Account of Former Times it appears to us, that Thus it always <hi>has been,</hi> and from reasoning on the Nature of the Thing, that Thus it necessarily <hi>must be:</hi> and therefore let us possess our Souls in Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Peace; and go on in the plain Paths of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness and Honesty, without Turning to the Right or Left, for whatever Men scornfully-Witty can say of us or to us.</p>
            <p>Let us beg of Him, <hi>who resisteth the Proud, but giveth Grace to the Lowly,</hi> let us beg of him to Bestow on us, to Preserve and Increase in us, that <hi>serious and humble</hi> Frame of Spirit, which alone can qualifie us for a Right Apprehension of the Truths and Mysteries of the Gospel; and which is therefore certainly Preferable to all Other Endowments of Mind, however the World may have misplac'd the greatest Part of its Esteem upon 'em.</p>
            <p>And let us, in order to this end, frequently take to our selves the humble Words of the <hi>Son of Syrach,</hi> and say; <hi>O Lord, Father and God of my Life, leave me not in Their Imagination, neither give me a proud Look; but turn away from Thy Servant an haughty Mind! Take away from me vain Hope and Concupiscence, and retain him in Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence that desireth continually to serve thee! Let not the Gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diness of the Belly, nor the Lust of the Flesh hold me, and give not Me thy Servant over to an Impudent Mind!</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:200282:14"/>
            <p>And as for Those, who contemn Us, and Our Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Principles, and who make us Their Derision daily, let us (in the Words of the Apostle) <hi>not cease to make mention of 'em in our Prayers, that the God of our Lord Jesus Christ, the Father of Glory, may give unto 'em the Spirit of Wisdom and Revelation to the Acknowledgment of him! The Eyes of their Understanding being enligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tened, that they may know what is the Hope of his Calling, and what the Riches of the Glory of his Inheritance in the Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>Advertisement.</head>
            <p>PRinted for <hi>Thomas Bennet.</hi> A Sermon on <hi>Praise and Thanksgiving</hi> before the Queen, at <hi>White-Hall, May</hi> 29. 1692.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Power of Charity to Cover sin,</hi> A Sermon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Governors of <hi>Bridewel</hi> and <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> Aug. 16. 1694.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Christian Religion Increas'd by Miracle,</hi> A Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon before the Queen, at <hi>White-Hall, Oct.</hi> 21. 1694. All Three by the same Author.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:200282:14"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>